Francis Baylies Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Francis Baylies Papers 1814-1843
MSS12096
Baylies, Francis, 1783-1852
150 items
5 containers
2.0 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Scholar, diplomat, politician, and historian. Primarily writings by Baylies relating to the American Revolution, the Confederation and the Constitution, Alexander Hamilton, and the administrations of George Washington, John Adams, and Thomas Jefferson.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, John, 1735-1826.; Baylies, Francis, 1783-1852.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804--Correspondence.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.
Organizations
Lexington (Sloop); Massachusetts. General Court. House of Representatives.; United States. Constitution.
Subjects
Auroras.; Fisheries--Falkland Islands.
Places
Falkland Islands--History.; Massachusetts--History--New Plymouth, 1620-1691.; Massachusetts--Politics and government.; United States--History--Confederation, 1783-1789.; United States--History--Constitutional period, 1789-1809.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States--Politics and government--1775-1783.; United States--Politics and government--1783-1789.; United States--Politics and government--1789-1809.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Historians.; Politicians.; Scholars.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Francis Baylies, scholar, diplomat, politician, and historian, were acquired by the Library of Congress in the nineteenth century. An additional item was given by David C. Mearns in 1961.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Francis Baylies are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1783, Oct. 16 Born, Taunton, Mass.
1810 Admitted to the bar and commenced law practice
1812 1820 Served as register of probate, Bristol County, Mass.
1821 Elected as Federalist, Seventeenth Congress
1822 Married Elizabeth Moulton Deming (died 1868)
1823 Elected as Jackson Federalist, Eighteenth Congress
1825 Elected as a Jacksonian, Nineteenth Congress
1827 1832 Served as member of the Massachusetts house of representatives
1830 Published An Historical Memoir of the Colony of New Plymouth... Boston: Hilliard, Gray, Little, and Wilkins
1832 Served as U.S. Chargé d'Affaires to Argentina
1835 Elected to Massachusetts house of representatives
1852, Oct. 28 Died, Taunton, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Francis Baylies (1783-1852) span the years 1814-1843. The papers contain Baylies's writings relating to the American Revolution, the Confederation and Constitution, Alexander Hamilton, and the administrations of George Washington, John Adams, and Thomas Jefferson. Other documents include transcripts of Alexander Hamilton letters, drafts of letters by Baylies, copies of diplomatic and naval correspondence on the voyage of the Lexington (sloop) and the Falkland Islands fisheries dispute, quotations from Baylies's book on the New Plymouth Colony, manuscript copies of documents relating to the business of the Massachusetts house of representatives, and a speech on the aurora borealis.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
- Copies of correspondence between George W. Slacum and the secretary of state, 1831-1832 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1827-1831, 1840 (Box 1)
- Manuscript quotations from An Historical Memoir of the Colony of New Plymouth..., circa 1843 (Box 1)
- Writings (Box 1)
  - Unpublished manuscripts (Box 1)
    - "History of the American Revolution, 1775-1784" (Box 1)
      - 1775-1777, (3 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1777-1785, (5 folders) (Box 2)
    - On Confederation and Constitution, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - "History of the Adminstration of George Washington," undated (Box 3)
    - "The Civil, Military, Legislative, Diplomatic & Miscellaneous History of the Administration of Thomas Jefferson," undated (Box 4)
    - "The Civil, Military, Legislative, Diplomatic & Miscellaneous History of the Administration of John Adams," undated (Box 4)
    - On Alexander Hamilton, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1814-circa 1831, (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Essays, undated (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous notes and notebooks, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Notes on (Box 5)
  - Adams, John, undated (Box 5)
  - Bristol Academy, Taunton, Mass., undated (Box 5)
  - Cobb, David, undated (Box 5)
  - Formation of the nations of Western Europe, undated (Box 5)
  - Hartford Convention of 1814-1815, undated (Box 5)
  - Northwest Territory, undated (Box 5)
  - Population, undated (Box 5)
- Plays, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Speech by Baylies, "Some Remarks on the Phenomina of the Aurora Borealis," undated (Box 5)